Ashish Panigrahi

• https://ashishpanigrahi.me

■ ashish.panigrahi@niser.ac.in • • paniash • in ashish-panigrahi99

About me

I am a 4^{th} year physics student studying at the **National Institute of Science Education and Research, Bhubaneswar, India**. I am interested in quantum physics & quantum computing with its application in the field of science and technology.

Nationality: Indian

Education

• National Institute of Science Education and Research (NISER)

Integrated Master's (CGPA till 6th semester: 9.13/10.0)

Bhubaneswar, India 2018 - 2023

• Maharishi Vidya Mandir Senior Sec. School All India Senior Secondary Certificate Examination (CBSE) - 95.6% Chennai, India $May\ 2018$

• PSG Public School
All India Secondary School Examination (CBSE) - CGPA 10

Coimbatore, India May 2016

Honors/Awards

• IBM Qiskit Advocate

2021

IBM Quantum

- Selected from a pool of global applicants.
- This achievement depicts a deep level of understanding with Qiskit including circuits, algorithms, simulators, qubits and noise.
- Through my contributions to the Qiskit and the quantum community, I have demonstrated an ability and commitment to educate and influence others by sharing ideas, knowledge and expertise in the field of quantum computing.
- National Graduate Physics Examination (National topper) Indian Association of Physics Teachers

2020

- Secured a score within the top 118 students among 12,000 candidates in the country.
- Department Topper (1st & 2nd year) School of Physical Sciences, NISER

2018-2020

• Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana

2017

Indian Institute of Science

Bengaluru, India

- A prestigious fellowship program funded by the Department of Science and Technology of the Government of India.
- National Talent Search Examination

2016

National Council of Education Research and Training

New Delhi, India

- A national level scholarship program offered by the Government of India.
- It is one of the oldest and most prestigious scholarship programmes in the country.

Academic exposure

• Qiskit Global Summer School IBM Quantum Virtual July-August 2020

- An intensive 2 week virtual summer school on quantum computation and designing quantum circuits and algorithms using Qiskit.
- Did hands-on coding exercises to learn various quantum algorithms, pulse level control of qubits and concepts in quantum chemistry.
- Also did a project on simulating the ground energy level of LiH molecule using quantum variational eigensolver.

• National Initiative on Undergraduate Science (Physics) Homi Bhabha Centre for Science Education, TIFR

Mumbai, Maharashtra June 2019

- Selected as one of top 70 students in the country to participate in this camp.
- An extensive 12-day course containing lectures, independent lab work and a field trip for 2 days.
- Lecture series on quantum mechanics, quantum information theory and quantum computation, basic condensed matter physics, many body physics, astronomy and astrophysics.
- About 30 hours of independent lab work.

Project experience

• Sixth Semester Project

Bhubaneswar, India April - July 2021

Superconducting spintronics group, NISER

- Project guide: Dr. Kartik Senapati, Reader-F, NISER
- Worked on a semester project on the topic, "Study of spin current in NM/HM bilayer and trilayer systems".
- The goal was to be able to detect spin current via a bilayer system involving Cu and Pt, using the method of electrical detection.

• Software Developer Internship

Remote

Quantum Brilliance, Australia

February - April 2021

- Project guide: Dr. Nariman Saadatmand, QBQE Product Manager
- Worked on QB's quantum emulator (QBQE) and enhanced functionality of its QAOA module using C++.

• Summer Project

Bhubaneswar, India

Institute of Physics, Bhubaneswar

May - June 2019

- Project guide: Dr. Debakanta Samal, Reader-F, Institute of Physics
- Reading project on "Study on anisotropic magnetoresistance".
- Topics covered: Origin of magnetoresistance, theory of magnetoresistance in real metals using the 2-band charge carrier model, origin of anisotropic magnetoresistance, its applications and current research scenario in the field.

Open-source contributions

• Qiskit Textbook

 GitHub

Learn Quantum Computation using Qiskit

April 2020 - Present

- Qiskit is IBM's software development kit for building software to interact with IBM's quantum devices and OpenQASM.
- The textbook is equivalent to a university level course for learning quantum computation and beyond.
- I have been an active contributor to this project with over 50+ commits since April 2020.

Licenses & Certifications

• IBM Certified Associate Developer Quantum Computation using Qiskit v0.2X

- This certification demonstrates fundamental knowledge of quantum computing concepts and the ability to express them using the Qiskit open source software development kit (SDK).
- Shows experience in using the Qiskit SDK from the Python programming language to create and execute quantum computing programs on IBM Quantum computers and simulators.

• Introduction to Quantum Computing Course

Qubit by Qubit

IBM Quantum & The Coding School

October 2020 - May 2021

 Developed a foundational understanding of quantum computing, with topics including introductory linear algebra, coding with Qiskit, quantum mechanics, quantum algorithms, and quantum applications.

Challenge Fall 2020 Achievement - Intermediate $IBM\ Quantum$

IBM

December 2020

- Demonstrated an ability to implement near-future quantum data structures and design a quantum game solver using Grover's algorithm.
- Showed an understanding of quantum circuits, the gates that comprise such circuits, Grover's algorithm, and qRAM (quantum random access memory) as a way to implement complex data structures.

\bullet CS-191x: Quantum Mechanics and Quantum Computation

edX

August 2020

University of California, Berkeley

- Coursework involved ranging from the basics of the qubit to quantum algorithms such as Grover's, Shor's etc. to the Bloch sphere and Schrödinger's wave equation.
- Final score: 97%

Volunteering

• Project Lovelace

Scientific programming problems

May 2021 - Present

- Project Lovelace is a platform to learn science through programming.
- Member of the team to add new problems and maintain the website (both frontend and backend).
- Website: https://projectlovelace.net

• Full-Stack Quantum Computation

 $Community\hbox{-}driven,\ open\hbox{-}source\ education\ resources$

December~2020~-~Present

- Part of the team as a curator of various articles on quantum technologies, submitted by volunteers.
- Website: https://fullstackquantumcomputation.tech

• Mentor

Avanti Fellows NGO

January - April 2019

- Duties included mentoring students from grades 11 and 12.
- My weekend work involved having a one-to-one discussion with students on physics and general advice on entrance exams.

Technical skills

Programming and scripting languages

C, C++, Bash, and Python (Libraries: Scipy, Numpy, Matplotlib, Sympy)

Markup languages

 $L\!\!^{A}\!T_{\!E}\!X,\, Markdown,\, Groff,\, HTML$

Quantum Frameworks

Qiskit, QuTiP, PennyLane

${\bf General\ computing\ tools}$

Vim, git, tmux, gnuplot

